Finding Aid for G. Donald Kennedy Papers 1928-1968
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
G. Donald Kennedy Papers
1928-1968
Kennedy, G. Donald (George Donald), 1900-
Civil engineer, served as Michigan state highway commissioner, chairman of the Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority and president of Portland Cement Company. Papers primarily document work with highway commission and Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority.
851011, Aa/2, AC
6 linear feet in 7 boxes
14 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The G. Donald Kennedy collection has come to the library in several accession, mainly in 1966 and 1967 with a smaller accession coming in 1982. Donor no. 4416
The collection is open for research.
G. Donald Kennedy was a prominent public official. Trained as a civil engineer, Kennedy served as Michigan state highway commissioner, chairman of the Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority, and as president of the Chicago-based Portland Cement Company. Kennedy was noted for his interest in the development of the Michigan's highway system. He was also a proponent of the need for constructing a bridge across the straits of Mackinac.
G. Donald Kennedy, civil engineer, was born in South Lyon, Michigan, on January 25, 1900. He graduated from Ann Arbor High School in 1917, and from the University of Michigan in 1921 with majors in political science and engineering.
Kennedy was registered as a professional engineer in Michigan and several other states, and had a distinguished career in structural, municipal, and highway engineering. During his career he was employed by Hoad and Decker, consulting engineers of Ann Arbor, and by the cities of Jackson and Pontiac as a municipal engineer. He planned the construction of the municipal airport in Pontiac and became an avid promoter of aviation. From 1933 to 1942 he served the Michigan State Highway Department as business manager, consulting engineer, deputy commissioner, and commissioner. He was Vice-President in Charge of Highway Development for the Automotive Safety Foundation from 1943 to 1949, and closed his career at the Portland Cement Association of Chicago, Illinois, where he was consulting engineer and assistant to the president, vice-president, executive vice-president, and president.
Kennedy also served on many boards and committees and was active in the Democratic Party. He managed the gubernatorial campaigns of Murray D. Van Wagoner and Frank Murphy. Among the positions he held were chairman of the Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority from 1938 to 1944, member of the Michigan Council of Defense during World War II, Vice-Chairman of the National Interregional Highway Committee from 1941 to 1944, President of the American Association of State Highway Officials from 1941 to 1942, member of the Board of Commissioners of the Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority from 1941 to 1945, member of the Highway Traffic Advisory Committee to the War Department, Consultant to the United States Senate Post-War Planning Committee, and member and Chairman of the Executive Committee of the Highway Research Board, National Research Council.
Among the honors received by Kennedy are the George S. Bartlett Award in 1948 for outstanding contribution to highway progress, and the University of Michigan Sesquicentennial Award in 1967. A roadside park near Charlevoix, Michigan, was named in his honor in 1961.
Kennedy died March 16, 1988.
The collection is arranged into ten series:
Personal/biographical -- Box 1
Correspondence -- Box 1
Speeches -- Boxes 1-2
Pontiac Municipal Engineer -- Box 2
Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority/Mackinac Bridge -- Box 3
Michigan State Highway Department -- Box 3-4
Other Organizational Affiliations -- Boxes 4-5
Published Materials -- Box 6
Photographs -- Box 7
Scrapbooks -- Outsize volumes
The papers, 1928-1968, of G. Donald Kennedy document his career in civil engineering, his participation in professional organizations, his activities as a state official, and as a supporter of the Michigan Democratic Party. The collection Includes correspondence, speeches, minutes, reports, articles, clippings, and photographs. The files relate to his work as municipal engineer in Pontiac, Michigan, with the Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority, the American Association of State Highway Officials, the Automotive Safety Foundation, and the Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority. The collection also includes papers relating to highway and airport construction, to economic mobilization during World War II, the Willow Run Bomber Plant, state Democratic Party matters, particularly the campaign visits of President Roosevelt to Michigan in 1936.
Subjects:
Aeronautics.; Airports--Michigan.; American Association of State Highway Officials.; Automotive Safety Foundation.; Bridges--Michigan.; Cement.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Engineers--Michigan.; Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority.; Kennedy, G. Donald (George Donald), 1900-1988; Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Mackinac Bridge Authority (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan. State Highway Dept.; Pontiac (Mich.); Presidents--United States--Election--1936.; Roads--Michigan.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Traffic engineering--Michigan.; Willow Run Bomber Plant.; World War, 1939-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Blue Water Bridge (Port Huron, Mich. and Sarnia, Ont.); Boat and ship industry.; Chrysler Corporation.; City of Cheboygan (Ship); City of Munising (Ship); City of Petoskey (Ship); Cut River Bridge (Mich.); Defense industry.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Dickinson, Luren Dudley, 1859-1943.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Ferries.; Mackinac Bridge (Mich.); Mackinac Island (Mich.); Mackinaw City (Mich.); Michigan. State Highway Dept.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Offices.; Pere Marquette No. 20 (Ship); Political elections--1936.; Political elections--1937.; Political elections--1941.; Politics and government--1921-1930.; Politics and government--1931-1940.; Politics and government--1941-1950.; Quarrying.; Roads--Michigan.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Saint Ignace (Mich.); Straits of Mackinac (Ship); Tanks (Military science); Traffic congestion.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.; Willow Run Bomber Plant.; Willow Run Expressway (Mich.); World War, 1939-1945.
Contributors:
Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957.; Cobo, Albert E. (Albert Eugene), 1893-1957.; Delano, Frederic A. (Frederic Adrian), 1863-1953.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Jeffries, Edward, 1900-1950; Litchfield, Edward H. (Edward Harold), 1914-1968.; MacDonald, Thomas H. (Thomas Harris), b. 1881.; Michelf, Rodolfo.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Sorensen, Charles E., 1881-1968.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Personal/Biographical Papers
  The Personal/biographical series consists of biographical information and folders pertaining to the various awards received by Kennedy throughout his career.
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
  - State Board of Registration, 1943-1966 (Box 1)
  - Honors
    - George S. Bartlett Award, 1948 (Box 1)
    - Naming of G. Donald Kennedy Roadside Park, 1961 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan Sesquicentennial Award, 1967 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series is a mixture of personal and professional communications mainly from the period when Kennedy was with the Portland Cement Association.
  - 1928-1968, 8 folders (Box 1)
    (lacking 1943)
  - 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - Letters received upon retirement from Portland Cement Association, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
- Speeches
  Kennedy kept his Speeches in binders. They are dated 1935 to 1965 and pertaining largely to issues of highways and transportation.
  - 1935-1945, 8 volumes (Box 1)
    (lacking 1938)
  - 1946-1965, 7 volumes (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous speeches (Box 2)
    (scattered dates)
- Pontiac, Michigan municipal engineer
  The files kept by Kennedy while Pontiac Municipal Engineer are minimal, consisting of reports and other documents pertaining to aviation and the construction of the Pontiac airport.
  - Reports on Water Supply, 1928; 1930 (Box 2)
  - Municipal Airport, 1928-1932 (Box 2)
  - Airports and Aviation, 1929-1961 (Box 2)
  - Reports on Michigan's Aviation Program, undated (Box 2)
- Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority/Mackinac Bridge
  The Mackinac Straits Bridge Authority/Mackinac Bridge series consists of files of correspondence and minutes of the authority from the period when Kennedy was chairman. There are also a few files of later dated material from the period following the construction of the bridge.
  - Correspondence and minutes, 1940-1960; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Dedication of Mackinac Straits Bridge, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Dedication of Plaque, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Reports, 1939; 1951 (Box 3)
  - Reports on engineering and traffic revenues, 1953 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    (includes testimony before congressional committee, 1939, and bonds for financing bridge construction)
- Michigan State Highway Department
  The Michigan State Highway Department series dates from 1924 to 1960 and consists of two subseries: Administrative Files and Background Information and Reports. There are reports in both subseries relating to the development of Michigan's highway system.
  - Administrative Files
    - Appointment to Consulting Highway Specialist, 1941 (Box 3)
    - Historical Retrospectives, 1970-1981 (Box 3)
    - Preliminary Report on Michigan's Plan for Highways, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Report on Automobile Weight Tax and Related Financial Studies, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Report on Township Road Relief, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Study on the Relocation of the Grand Trunk Railroad, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Report on the Re-certification of Total Township Road Mileage in the State of Michigan, 1935 (Box 3)
    - Negotiations with Governor Murphy for State Appropriations, 1938 (Box 3)
    - Report on Public Works Commission, 1938 (Box 3)
    - Report on Initial Designation of Routes to be included in the Federal and Secondary System, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Inauguration of G. Donald Kennedy as State Highway Commissioner, 1941 (Box 3)
    - Report on Military Access Roads in Michigan, 1941 (Box 3)
    - Request for Reconstruction Finance Corporation Loan for Detroit Crosstown National Defense Motorway, 1941 (Box 3)
    - Schedule of Commissioner Kennedy, 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Background Information and Reports
    - Materials relating to the Detroit-Freeway System, 1924-1955 (Box 3)
    - Report on Center Line Striping, 1938 (Box 3)
    - Report on History of Highway Development in Ohio, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Report by Michigan State Safety Commission on Proposed Integrated War Program, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Report on Weights and Sizes of Motor Vehicles, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Report on Highway Transportation System in Oregon, 1948 (Box 3)
    - Materials and Clippings relating to Toll Roads and Expressways in Michigan, Illinois, and Indiana, 1951-1960 (Box 4)
    - Materials and Clippings relating to Toll Roads and Expressways in Illinois, Colorado, New York, and California, 1951-1960 (Box 4)
    - Materials and Clippings relating to Toll Roads and Expressways In Connecticut, Ohio, Texas, and Pennsylvania, 1951-1960 (Box 4)
    - Report to the Motor Carrier Industry, 1952 (Box 4)
    - Essay on How to Plan and Pay for the Safe and Adequate Highways We Need, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Report, The Washo Road Test, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Report, Parking as a Factor in Business, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Studies on Highways in Cleveland, Kalamazoo, Albuquerque, and states of Ohio and California, 1953-1955 (Box 4)
    - Paper on Motor Vehicle Production and Use in United States, 1895-1960; 1960 (Box 4)
- Other Organizational Affiliations
  Kennedy worked with, and was a member of, numerous professional and civic organizations. Information about his activities with this groups will be found in the Other Organizational Affiliations series. Some of the more substantial subseries here pertain to his work with the American Association of State Highway Officials, the Automotive Safety Foundation, the National Interregional Highway Committee, and the Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority. There is also a series representing Kennedy's association with various organizations and committees.
  - American Association of State Highway Officials
    - Correspondence, 1941-1942 (Box 4)
    - Notes on Committee Meetings, 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Automotive Safety Foundation
    - Letters of congratulation received upon appointment as Vice President, 1943. (Box 4)
    - Automotive Safety Foundation Manual, 1943 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence and Meetings with Brady Gentry, President of American Association of State Highway Officials, 1943; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Article by G. Donald Kennedy, Annual Highway Need of $4 Billion Places Emphasis on Planning, 1948 (Box 4)
    - Trustees Meeting, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Materials relating to President's Highway Safety Conference, 1949-1954 (Box 4)
      includes photographs of event
    - Pamphlets on traffic safety, and Alfred P. Sloan Awards for Highway Safety, 1953-1955 (Box 4)
    - Dinner Honoring Hoffman and Fraser, 1948 (Box 4)
  - National Interregional Highway Committee
    - Minutes and correspondence, 1940-1959 (Box 5)
    - Data on Tentative Systems Selected by the Staff for Consideration by the National Interregional Highway Committee, 1941 (Box 5)
  - Huron-Clinton Metropolitan Authority
    - Correspondence, 1942-1945 (Box 5)
    - Board of Commissioners minutes and correspondence, 1941-1945; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Professional Activities
    - Exhibits Attesting to Qualifications, 1918-1938 (Box 5)
    - Engineering Society of Detroit, 1936-1942 (Box 5)
    - Democratic Party Politics, 1936-1945 (Box 5)
    - American Road Builders Association, 1940-1967 (Box 5)
    - Highway Traffic Advisory Committee to the War Department, 1941-1944 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Postwar Construction, 1944-1945 (Box 5)
    - Centennial of Engineering, 1952 (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan Centennial of Engineering, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Metropolitan Housing and Planning Council, 1957-1965 (Box 5)
    - National Research Council, Division of Engineering and Industrial Research and Committee on Urban Research, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
    - Eno Foundation, 1961-1964 (Box 5)
    - Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Portland Cement Association
      - Advertising and correspondence with foreign associates, 1962-1967 (Box 5)
      - Presentation to state road commission of West Virginia, 1958 (Box 5)
      - Miscellanea (Box 5)
    - Chamber of Commerce of the United States, Association Committee, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
    - Conferences in Europe, 1957 (Box 5)
      (International Concrete Road Congress and the International Road Federation)
    - Conference in Europe, 1962 (Box 5)
      (International Road Federation)
- Printed material (authored in part by GDK)
  There is a small series of Printed Material that was authored in whole or in part by Kennedy. Dating from the 1940s and 50s, the items concern highway development.
  - Modern Urban Highways, 1944 (Box 6)
  - The Story of Highways, 1944 (Box 6)
  - Interstate Highways, circa 1944-1945 (Box 6)
  - Engineering Facts and a Future Program. A Study for the California Legislature, 1946 (Box 6)
  - Highways in Washington's Future, 1948 (Box 6)
  - $50,000,000,000 Challenge to the Engineering Profession. American Engineer, 1955 (Box 6)
  - The Effect of the Expanded Federal Highway Program on Traffic Engineering, 1956 (Box 6)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series dates from the mid-1930s to around 1970. The photographs have been arranged by topic and include photos of Michigan State Highway Department projects, including the Blue Water, Mackinac, and Cut River Bridges, images of ferries crossing the Straits of Mackinac, and photos of the Willow Run Expressway. Other photos pertain to Kennedy's involvement with the Democratic Party, especially the campaigns of Murray D. Van Wagoner. Some notable images are of visits to Michigan by President Franklin Roosevelt, Henry A. Wallace, and James A. Farley. Also of interest are photos of the Chrysler Tank Arsenal, and the personnel, offices, and work areas of the Michigan State Highway Department.
  - Awards and dedications (Box 7)
  - Conferences and dinners (Box 7)
  - Democratic Party
    - Campaigns (Box 7)
      (includes Henry Wallace, Franklin Roosevelt, Frank Murphy, Murray Van Wagoner)
    - Conference, Mackinac Is, 1938; negatives only (Box 7)
      (includes James A. Farley, Frank Murphy)
  - Detroit-During transit strike, 1941 (Box 7)
  - Eau Claire, Wisconsin-Airplane crash, 1938 (Box 7)
  - Friends and colleagues (Box 7)
  - Mackinac Bridge
    - Artists' sketches (Box 7)
    - Dedication of plaque, 1960 (Box 7)
  - Mackinac Straits ferries and Mackinaw City docks (Box 7)
  - Mackinaw City-Ferry traffic, Labor Day, 1941 (Box 7)
  - Port Huron (Box 7)
  - Portraits St. Ignace-Ferry traffic, Labor Day, 1941 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Albums
    - AASHO 27th annual convention, Detroit, 1941 (Box 7)
      (includes bus caravan and quarry at Alpena)
    - Michigan State Highway Department, 1935; 2 volumes (Box 7)
      (includes portraits of employees and photos of offices and other work areas)
- Scrapbooks
  The Kennedy collection includes fourteen volumes of outsize Scrapbooks, 1933-1942, containing photographs, clippings, and other materials dealing mainly with Kennedy's career and his work with the Michigan State Highway Department and the state Democratic Party.
  - Volume I, 1933-1935 (Volume 1)
    (Subjects and material include: Michigan Highway and Road Commission; Annual Report of the American Association of State Highway Officials, 1935)
  - Volume II, September 1935-August 1936 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: Political campaigns; Democratic National Convention 1936, Picture of J. Earle Brown, Murray D. Van Wagoner, D.C. Roper, E.F. Paxton, and T. I. Fray; Sports programs; notice of dedication of roads)
  - Volume III, April 1937-February 1938 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: Photographs of Mackinac Island including one portrait of Gov. Frank Murphy)
  - Volume IV, February-July 1938 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: Photographs of ship [Pere Marquette] through June 1938 and photograph of gathering in May 1938)
  - Volume V, August 1938-February 1939 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: convention programs, sport programs photographs of New York City and Blue Water Bridge)
  - Volume VI February-December 1939 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: photograph of large group of men in 1939 including Van Wagoner and Kennedy, picture of New York World's Fair and large photograph of Kennedy)
  - Volume VII, 1940 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: photograph of James H. Farley, promotional license plate, Democratic Convention Programs, State Highway Department pamphlets and photographs, articles and letters relating to Kennedy's appointment as highway commissioner, photographs from testimonial dinner for Gov. Dickinson; Blue Water Bridge photographs)
  - Volume VIII, 1936-1937 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: autographed photograph of Murray D. Van Wagoner; Detroit News, October 18,1936 the 10th Anniversary issue of the Michigan State Digest; photographs of Michigan officials, articles and miscellanea relating to the inauguration of Frank Murphy; also election materials 1936 and 1937.)
  - Volume I, circa January-August 1941 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: political photographs and programs relating to Kennedy's campaign for Highway Commissioner; Van Wagoner inauguration; Chrysler Tank Arsenal photographs.)
  - Volume X (Vol. X), 1942 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: war-time articles relating to conventions and campaigns; also State Highway Department letters and business; shipyard visit photos.)
  - Volume XI, circa September 1941-October 1941 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: articles on Kennedy's alleged corruption as Highway Commissioner and State Highway conventions and programs; Cut River Bridge.)
  - Volume XII, circa October 1936 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: newspaper articles and photographs relating to Franklin D. Roosevelt, his staff and his appearances in Michigan; also photographs of F.D.R. in Detroit and with Frank Murphy and Kennedy; letter to Kennedy pertaining to the arrangements for F.D.R.'s visit to Michigan.)
  - Volume XIII, 1940-1942 (Box 7)
    (Subjects and material include: Press Clippings relating to Kennedy and Highway Commission of Michigan.)
  - Volume XIV, undated
    (Subjects and material include: description and map of Willow Run Bomber Plant; photographs of Willow Run Traffic problems; and plans of first expressway.)
Selective Index of Correspondents
Brown, Prentiss Marsh, 1889-1973.
April 29, 1935.
Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957.
September 18, 1933.
Cobo, Albert Eugene, 1893-1957
October 25, 1955.
Delano, Frederick Adrian, 1863-1953.
February 24, 1942; March 2, 12, 16, 20, 1942.
Farley, James Aloysius, 1888-1976.
October 9, 1937.
Jefferies, Edward J., 1900-1950.
April 17, 1942
Litchfield, Edward Harold, 1914-1968.
October 23, 1947; November 20, 1947; December 2, 1947.
MacDonald, Thomas Harris, 1881-1957.
November 25, 1938; December 1, 1938.
Michelf, Rodolfo
August 1, 1941.
Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.
October 6, 1936, October 16, 1937.
Osborn, Chase Salmon, 1860-1949.
January 10, 1940.
Romney, George Wilcken. 1907-
November 26, 1941; December 29, 1949.
Sorenson, Charles E., 1881-1968.
July 23, 1945; August 2, 1945; October 13, 21, 1941.
Van Wagoner, Murray Delos,1898-
December 15, 1942
Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.
November 13, 1941.
Williams G. Mennen, 1911-
July 14, 1949; December 9, 1949.